Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and we are
going to be delving farther into
the math skills to ace chemistry.
Today we're going to be
looking at logarithms.
So with logarithms, whenever we hear
that term, it can be very daunting,
especially if you've had it in basic,
had it in basic algebra, you might have
realized like, oh, you did not maybe
have a good experience the first time.
Um, but really what is, what is
all about is that it's a lot easier
of a concept than you realize.
Is that logarithms, what they are,
so log for short, we're not talking
about the piece of wood here, but
when it comes to logs or a logarithm
is that these are math functions.
And now with that function, what it does
is it tells you how many times a base is
multiplied by itself to reach that number.
So what do I mean by that to kind of
make that make a little bit more sense?
So most of the time in chemistry,
we're using a log 10 function.
So this is referred to as the base.
Now in order to make this operation make
sense, we have this 1000 number here.
So we are going to use the log to take
the function and we want to know how
many times this 10 fit in this number.
So if you think about that, right, you do
10 times 10, that's 100 times 10 again.
And that is 1000.
It went into that three times to
see how many times to the base fit.
So the answer would be three.
So that's kind of the idea here is
that we're trying to figure out,
well, can we make a simpler system?
So, what, how is that
exactly used in chemistry?
Let's take a look.
In
chemistry, it's very common
that we use scientific notation
to denote different scales.
And the general reason why we use
that is because it helps simplify
a lot of the numbers we use.
So, one thing is though, we commonly use
a negative log base scale to determine
how acidic or how basic a substance is.
Which is known as pH, right?
You use pH in chemistry, in
biology, in environmental
science, you use it all the time.
So, with the pH, all it is, is equals to
the negative log, uh, and we're taking the
function of the concentration of the acid.
So, what we do is we plug
in the molarity of H plus.
Into the log function and we
will get a pH and we can do the
same thing for P O H as well.
Now the point of this video is not to
talk about pH and the concepts behind it.
That's another video which I would
recommend referring to, but we are just
going to look at the math and how to
use your calculator to do log functions.
Let's go into this a little bit farther,
which calculator you're used to.
So we're going to be using a TI 36 X pro.
So Texas instrument calculator,
and I'll also be getting tips and
tricks on like the TI 83 and the
TI 88, which are other calculators,
which are very similar as well.
So what we'll be doing is we'll be
showing my calculator display here.
So I'll be kind of showing you
the different buttons to hit.
So that way you can get an idea of
exactly what this guy looks like.
So that way you can follow along with
your calculator and I would recommend
trying to practice it along with me.
So that way you can see, are
you entering them in right?
Cause you don't want to do all the work.
And then put the wrong answer on the
exam, even though you knew how to do it.
It's just discouraging and not fun.
So let's go forward and take a
look at some examples of this.
So with our first example,
we're going to find the negative
log of the following numbers.
And we're going to also be
determining our sig figs.
So the first thing is, is
let's talk about the sig figs.
So when we are doing these sig
figs are a little different
when it's talking about logs.
So the whole idea is you count
the number of sig figs you have.
And that's going to represent how many
decimal places you have in your pH value.
So we have three on the left hand
side, so that means you're going
to have three decimals on this pH.
So if we were to do this, so let's
bring up our calculator to solve this.
The first thing is, is
how do we end up using it?
So the first thing is, is hitting our
negative button, so that way we make
sure that we do use a negative log.
Now the log button is up here on the top
left hand side of your calculator, so
you can kind of see the log button here.
And one thing about it is, you'll notice
that there's two different things listed.
You have ln and log.
So if I hit that one time That is
a log, but it's not the right one.
This is wrong.
This is a natural log.
We use this for different
algebra applications and for
more advanced chemistry purposes.
Um, so what we would do is we got
to hit the button one more time
and then the log will pop up.
So you want to make sure you check.
Now, if you accidentally hit it
too many times and this pops up,
uh, what this allows you to do is
you can actually define your base
value, which for us is 10, Um, but
the last one that was previously
up here was the exact same thing.
So if you just hit it again, it
will pop up the negative log.
So now the whole idea is we're
going to plug in our numbers.
So we have 1.
00, right, and then we would do
times 10, and we're going to raise
that using our power function
right here to the negative fourth.
So we hit negative again, hit four.
We want to move our cursor over so
we can end the parentheses, right?
You want to use parentheses
as much as you can.
So now we have the following value.
You want to check.
We see that everything's
plugged in, right?
You don't want to blindly this
show to start plugging and chugging
numbers, not understand them, right?
So when we hit equal, we'll
get four, which makes sense.
It tells you what the power is when
this is equal to its regular value.
So we have four and we
want three decimals.
So it'd be 4.
0000.
Which would represent our theoretical
pH if we had a concentration of H plus.
So let's go to the next
one and do another.
So I have 0.
00001.
So if I were to do this, we're
going to do the same idea.
So we still hit that negative log.
We'll make sure the LOG pops up.
And now we will plug in our values.
So we need 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 zeros, then 1.
So we want to just double
check that we have everything.
In parentheses, it equals.
and we'll have our value.
So this tells you that that
decimal place moved over six
times, which is what our pH is.
Um, being that we had a total of one
decimal place, or sorry, one sig fig,
that means we're going to have one
decimal place with our number, so 6.
0.
All right, for the next one, one
thing we can see here is that we
have two sig figs, so that means
we'll have two decimal places.
So when we do this, so we'll
clear our work, we have negative
log again, we'll make sure we
have the log, now we'll put in 5.
0, we'll times that by 10 to the
negative 7, make sure everything
plugs in, everything looks fine.
Now, we're going to hit, end our
parentheses, and we'll hit enter,
and now this is when it starts
to be values that go between pHs.
You can have values between,
because acidity is a range, right?
It goes from 0 to 14, typically.
So being that we had 2, we're going
to want 2 decimal places, so we'll
put 6, and then we'll put 3, 0, and
we're going to be rounding here.
We see it's next to a 1, so
we keep it just where it is.
Alright, our last one.
We have negative log again, so
we're going to plug that in, hit 6.
0, and we're going to do times 10 to
the negative 12th, we're going to end
parentheses, and now we have our value.
So now currently we have 11.
22, so we want two decimal places,
so we are going to write 11.
22,
answer.
So this is how you go
from concentration to pH.
Now, what about going backwards?
Can you do that too?
Let's take a look.
So when it comes to canceling a
function, this is the same idea as
like multiplying versus dividing, or
if you have something that's squared
and then you square root it to cancel.
Well, in terms of logs, we have
an antilog in order to cancel it.
Now, the antilog is using
So whatever value that is.
Now, being for us, We're assuming that
this is a, as 10 to a power, right?
So whenever we have negative
log, we just use 10 to the
negative pH to cancel that out.
Now how exactly do we use
that with our calculator?
Well, that's a lot, a
little bit simpler to use.
So, when it comes to your, the TI
36, so the calculator we're using
here, you have a couple of different
options for how to cancel out your
values, and I'll show both of them.
There is a button that's designed
for this, and I don't think that
the creators of this calculator
really put it in the best location.
It's close, but it's not how,
like, the graphing calculators do.
Many of those will actually show, it
will be, you'll have a second button
on your calculator and it's generally
the function that's the second
button is how you can cancel out all
the functions on your calculator.
It's actually really nice.
So let's take a look at exactly
where that is and how we'll do that.
So if I put my calculator back on right
now, so if we see the log button, which
is right here on the top, so you'll
see right below it is that here is
this E button and then the power 10.
These are the opposites of natural
log, which is the E function,
and then 10 to the power.
So you could just hit this button twice
to get 10 to the power of your pH.
Now the other way you can do it is
you could simply just type in 10
and then put your power button and
then plug it in this way as well.
That's usually the easier way because
probably 99 percent of students
are used to using that already.
Um, when it comes to their functions,
let's do a couple examples together
and then we'll be on our way.
So let's find our theoretical
H plus concentration based
on our, on our pH values.
So we're going to use
the antilog to do that.
So the thing here is the sig
figs are based on a number
of decimal places you have.
Okay.
Thanks.
So like on the first example, right, we
have two decimals, so that means that
your concentration is going to be two
sig figs as well when we calculate that.
So sig figs are always important,
especially if you have to
record them digitally and a
lot of your homeworks and labs.
So let's take a look.
Let's use our calculator
to actually do this.
So if I bring up my calculator, so
before I still have the 10 function
here, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to hit the negative sign.
So that's really important.
Are you going to get a value
that doesn't make any sense?
Then we'll put 7.
40, so put that whole value in, and
then all we have to do is hit equals.
And now what this shows you
is how small your value is.
So what we have is our 4 value,
and being that it's going to be 4.
0.
Then we just got to move that to
a power, which we got to count
how many spots does this move.
Now, if you're lucky, maybe
your calculator has how many
spots that's going to move.
But for me, uh, I always go
to the old fashioned way.
So we're going to count.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8 spots.
So we have 4.
0 times 10 to the negative
8, our first value.
Let's go into another.
So the next one, we have 3.
2.
So what we are going to do is I'll
show you how to use the other way.
So we're going to do the 10 button.
So we're going to hit that
twice to make sure it says 10.
And now what we'll do is
we'll raise that to 3.
52.
We'll hit equal, and now we
have our new number here.
So being that we had two decimal
places, we need two sig figs.
So we are going to say 3.
0 times 10, and we need
to count how many spots.
So we have that it's four
positions that moved.
0 times 10 to the negative 4.
And remember, this represent, these
represent molarities is what these shows.
So remember units, your
professors expect that.
Now for the next part, right?
So one more.
So if I do the next one, we would, so
let's clear our work and now we have
10 and we're going to raise that to
the power and we're going to say 12.
240, we'll hit equals and now
we have a very, very big number.
Now why is it so large?
Have I forgotten anything
while doing this?
Notice I forgot my negative sign, right?
These should be small concentrations.
They shouldn't be anything
that's massive, right?
10 to the 12th molarity isn't feasible.
So let's fix that.
So what we'll do is I'll hit my 10 again.
I'll raise that to essentially
the power in order to fix that.
So let's do that.
And now we've got to hit our negative 12.
240.
Okay.
So now when I change that, we kind of see,
see how different the values are, right?
Almost 10 to the 12th.
This one's 10 to the negative 13th,
it's, it's supposed to be tiny.
So especially when you have a
high pH, it should be very small.
So when we do this, right,
we have three decimal places,
so we'll have three sig figs.
So we're going to have 5.
75 and then we're going
to hit 10 to the negative.
13.
Malarity will be your answer
and let me move that over so
you can see the whole thing.
And that will be how
you would convert that.
So this has been my demonstration
on how to show this with logs.
I hope you kind of like this, something
different using my calculator for once.
Um, let me know if you, if this made
sense to you and if this helped.
Um, and if you do need any help,
just reach out to me, he can just
send me a message or comment below.
If this is your first time here, please
look that like and subscribe button.
And if you need more help with math,
I have an entire math playlist,
which I would highly recommend
to help you with chemistry.
Um, I know a lot of math is really
scary, but my goal is to try
to make it a little less scary.
All right.
I hope this helped and I hope
to see you again in the future.
Bye now.